hi welcome back to negotiate course
number three
and we're gonna start a new chapter now
uh it's chapter 10
and it has a great name and we'll see
the name here
uh
it's called
an examination
or an investigation
into fire
and firewood
and we're still getting this argument
you see there's still this argument that
okay
until the young lady with the telescope
looks at the stars
we cannot call her an astronomer
so looking at the stars must happen
before she comes out of her house
before the astronomer comes out of her
house okay it has to
all right so there's some confusion
there and the other guy says
listen
i got a solution let's talk about
menthol pushing let's talk about fire
and firewood let's talk about fire
and firewood and according to me that's
going to clarify everything we will
solve these problems
if we just look at the example
of fire
and firewood and mainly those guys like
the lower abhidharma guys
who want to say that the eye was there
first
and then there was a scene the
astronomer was wandering around
and then they looked at a star
and they were called an astronomer even
before they looked at the stars right
that's their idea
they say
our position is supported
by the example of fire
and firewood the relationship between
fire
and firewood now to really appreciate
this chapter
i'd like to
explore with you first
let's do our getting to know sanskrit
assignment
and let's look at four sanskrit words
that are going to help us understand
this chapter okay
uh the first word is indana say indana
okay the tibetan is pushing
and uh this intana
comes from a root and you see that
square root symbol
id
or ind
which means to kindle or to set fire to
set fire to something okay
and i think it's related to the
indo-european which is kind of an older
root system
uh called ed which means to eat and
sometimes ants drop out
like it becomes ed in indo-european
and it means to eat and some cognates or
some english examples are edible
and eat and obese
and they all have the same root ed which
is related to the sanskrit root id
which means to burn uh the kindle part
uh which means to burn something
is related i think it uh has
is the precursor
of a root uh kanb
which means to burn and you see it
cunned in incandescent
candle
kindle
and i think there was an ancient s
before it which is skunned or shunned
and that came into the word shine
so all of these words for burning
uh id and ed khand and skund
uh all related to burning shund
all related to bernie okay
now
we were talking about the eye
uh looking at something at an object
okay so michael's eye
looks at
the juice michael's eye looks at the
orange juice okay the orange colored
juice
and you have three distinct things you
have the
that the do were which in which in
charlie llama calls
the agent let's say the one who
undertakes the object action
and then you have the object of the
action which is called the near limb
baja nero ninja
and then you have the action itself
meaning the object of the action
the agent of the action and this and the
action which is seeing in this case now
i challenge you
in the case of a fire
uh
who's the agent and who's the act who's
the object of the age of the agent okay
who's the agent in the case of a fire
uh and i'll give you some choices here
okay here's the first choice
indana
the wood okay is the wood
uh the agent
is the wood
like the eye
which does seize the object
because the wood
feeds the fire
okay there's a possibility
all right or let's go on to the next
sounds good word here uh which is agni
and as you guys probably know agni means
fire
and uh
you what's interesting is it comes from
a
verbal root ugh
which means to move like a snake like
this okay so the flames
are
[Music]
they're dancing dancing
agni means dancing agni means fire okay
and
in the indo-european again you have
these words for driving and movie
related moving related to aj that we had
before
and then you have the cognates act
active
agile and agent all coming from the same
root as ugg
to move and get things done okay
and then there's a suffix ni which makes
a nouns
out of verbs so agni means fire
and in english you get the words ignite
and ig
igneous meaning made from fire stone
made from fire
so that's the fire now again so so far
we have firewood
and we have fire
is it that the fire acts on the firewood
or is it that the firewood creates the
fire
which is the agent
with the eye it's easy the eye sees the
bottle
the bottle is the object the seeing is
the verb
and the eye is the subject
but in the case of a fire
who's the doer and what's done is the
fire the
the result of the
wood
or is it that the fire acts on the moon
is the f is the wood the object of the
fire
or is the wood the agent of the fire
okay you gotta think about it it's it's
confusing to me it's confusing
okay let's do a couple more words
and then we'll get to the real class
uh
okay and that means sekba it means
berlin okay the burning
okay so the fire burns the wood
can we say that
or the wood feeds the fire
okay
but anyway
is the root here which means to burn
i think it's related to
and then dhs sometimes change the f in
english which is f
and then to make it a
to make it an agent you have to call it
a
and then i think fire
and a a parallel case
is where der which became dharma
which means to hold something it comes
into the word
firm
and it's also the root for the word tree
because
trees were
the most immovable thing in the ancient
world
you couldn't move a tree okay so there
you go
yeah and
one more word for you guys in this
chapter
they're gonna talk about
fire burning wood until the wood is used
up and then the fire
here's the next word
nirvana okay isn't that interesting
so you always hear about nirvana
meaning to blow out
a candle
but here in the garjana in this chapter
he's using it
without reference to liberation it just
means
the fire went out nirvana okay it blew
itself out okay it it burned itself out
the fire burned itself out okay so
nirwana nirwana
and by the way the v in sanskrit is more
of a almost like a w
the tibetan is
which is a meaning translation and not a
literal translation
which means to go beyond grief
and here's the parts of the word nirvana
which i want you to learn okay
nis is a prefix which means
not
and it means out and down meaning
something degenerates until it's gone
uh and then you have the words nether
beneath and underneath okay
comes from this one needs to blow
that's an easy one for english cognates
you have fan
vent
and wind okay so blow out
is nirvana and it's i think it's
exciting in this
chapter
that we see nirvana used
only as a fire being blown out okay
and that that gives you a nice insight
into the
idea
of blowing out your anger at your
husband
because you realize he's coming from you
okay
that's nirvana okay
all right let's go back to the beginning
of this chapter 10
right
and we're gonna go through the
verses
one by one now the first verse
is traditionally split into two okay the
first verse
is traditionally treated
uh first to tibetan lines and then the
second two tibetan lines
and by the way uh
the sanskrit
still exists which is exciting if you
want to learn sanskrit
this book is a great text to learn
sanskrit from
i don't emphasize learning sanskrit
because most of the sanskrit is gone
so you know whereas in tibetan you have
maybe 500 000 important books in in
sanskrit you have a few hundred
maybe okay so i i don't know if it's
worth the effort
to spend uh six seven years learning
sanskrit
uh
you know
that tibetan is exactly
the same as the sanskrit i rarely really
really see any difference okay
all right
here we go first half of the first verse
uh
pushing me in
the first the way that nagarjuna
explores
the other guy's example right the other
guy says
look you can understand all your
questions in the garjana if you just use
the example of a fire and the firewood
and the interaction of the fire and the
firewood you're getting all complicated
you don't have to do it okay
if you just think about how a fire
consumes firewood
then then everything's clear the
discussion
of whether the little girl had to be
there first
or the looking at the stars had to be
there first and then the little girl was
an astronomer later
the whole discussion is decided
by fire and firewood just stick to fire
and firewood and the guardian says not
really
you know he's like i don't think so well
what's wrong with that in the garden
well
is the fire separate from the firewood
or not
is the fire a separate thing than the
firewood okay what do you guys think
i mean okay listen the garcia says
listen either the firewood is the fire
or the firework is not the fire which
one
and he says okay let's say you say the
same thing while they're not okay i mean
you can't burn yourself on the firewood
if it's not you know
okay so let's let's let's eliminate one
possibility
from the beginning we can say
that the firewood
is not the fire they're not the same
thing okay so here it says pushing me
now if the firework would were the fire
che papodan
then the
agent
then the burner and the burning would be
the same thing okay the burning would be
the burner
if you take the wood to be the cause of
the fire
then the wood would be the burning okay
then the wood would be the burning so
that's it's not possible
that the fire and the wood are the same
thing
so let's eliminate that possibility
let's go on to the possibility that the
fire and the wood are
not the same thing and that they're
separate okay we go to the second half
of the first uh
oh and by the way um
that picture we missed a picture here i
was supposed to explain a picture here
people looking at a campfire okay
and i don't know where i grew up arizona
it's very popular to go out in the
desert and make a small fire small fire
not this big one
and
you know and you sit around the campfire
and you look at the fire okay so
that the guy says
the other guy says look
uh
what the eye does when it looks at a
star
is not unreal it's real meaning for him
it's self-existent
it comes from its own side why
because a fire and what it burns are
real okay so he says
when somebody looks at a star
it's really happening
because
it's really happening when fire burns
wood same thing same thing rigpa
godzilla means parallel reasoning all
right
okay next
verse second part of oh by the way uh
one more picture before that
uh
the guardians says
if the fire was the wood
then the person making a pot out of clay
would be the pot okay
all right and that's easy to understand
it's one of the few easy things to
understand in regards
okay that's clear
if the fire was the firewood
then this girl would be a pot
okay then what makes the thing would be
the thing if if
if the fire is the wood that it burns
then the potter is the pot that it makes
and this girl would be a pot and this
girl would be in this girl's own hands
or something like that okay all right
not possible
all right let's go to the second half of
the first verse all right
uh
if the wood and the fire are separate
okay now you gotta think of
here's a principle when you're reading
the gaja
is the fire separate from the wood or
not
yeah it's separate from the food
is it self existently separate from the
wound
you see now because the guardians are
going to keep pulling out this word
self-existently without an observer with
karmic seeds in their mind is the word
separate from the fire
and the guardian says no
they're not separate from their own side
okay
so you have to remember that
if the wood
was distinct from the fire
then they would not overlap
uh they would never make contact okay
when i say overlap i may make contact
gesla it's not the same thing
to touch something and to overlap is
different look here's contact
and here's overlapping
but you gotta understand that if they
make contact
some part has to overlap okay some part
has to overlap why
there has to be a point of contact in
mathematics
a point
is a
is a single spot that has no width and
no length
but in reality if something touches
there has to be a point in contact there
has to be
so many milli millimeters
of a place where they overlap okay where
they occupy the same spot
or you couldn't have contact there can't
be contact okay
so it says uh
if the fire and the wood
never make contact meaning they are
separate if they are different from each
other if they never make contact
well then you're going to have fires
popping out all over the place where
there's no wood
but keep going there's a fire right
there why there's no wood yeah you don't
need wood why separate
they don't have to touch
there doesn't have to be wood in the
room for a fire to break out why
because all fires happen
what do you mean all fires happen
fires happen
where there's wood right yeah
so they touch right no they can't touch
why not they can't overlap okay so
they're separate what's the problem with
that well then you could have a fire
in this room if you had firewood in the
next room okay because they don't have
to touch
if they don't have to overlap then the
fire could be anywhere and the wood
could be anywhere then you'd have fires
breaking out all over the place no no no
they have to touch okay if they have to
touch they have to make contact yeah
then they have to overlap right then the
fire is the wood
no
look you can have it both ways the guy's
just like pulling his hair out that's
what happened to me
if they make contact
then some tiny part of the fire has to
be the firework
no i don't want that okay so they never
made contact right
okay so then watch out you've got to
have a fire extinguisher in your toilet
for your toilet because the fire might
pop out in the toilet
no there's water there just i don't care
a fire can happen anywhere it doesn't
have to touch the wood okay all right if
you're not confused yet i didn't do my
job
next verse and he he combines uh verse
two and verse three okay uh who's he
not only would fires break out
in in inside your toilet
uh
they would also burn forever
why because they don't burn from the
wood they just burn from the cells
because the wood never touches the fire
okay no the fire does touch the wood
okay then they overlap
right and the wind is the fire and the
fire is the word right
at some point
no no they're separate okay then watch
out
when you take a poop because the fire
the water might catch on fire
well i didn't say that yeah you did you
said the fire could happen without
firing i didn't say that yeah you did
you said it didn't have to touch the
firing yeah i did say that okay so the
firing can be in the other room the fire
could be in the toilet be careful when
you take a poop
okay uh something else is going on
something's fishy
what's going on maybe a separate entity
is causing the fire in the firewood
and maybe the firework has nothing to do
with the fire and maybe the mantra has
nothing to do with curing the cancer
maybe they're both coming from somewhere
else
okay i thought about i need to go
then not only would your toilet break on
fire but doctor means it would never go
out
because there's no wood
it just burned by itself
okay uh bartek you name injunction
furthermore
uh
you could have fires without any
fuel okay
and
somebody may need a girl and you
wouldn't have to go through the effort
of collecting firewood because you could
have a fire without the firewood so why
go through all the trouble of finding
firewood or buying oil
for your car gasoline for your car
because it's going to burn without the
gasoline the engine is going to burn
without the gasoline okay
then he gives another verse and i was
confused
when i first read it because it seems
like he repeats the same thing but i
tell you if you look at it carefully
you will see that verse three is a
justification in verse two okay and you
can you can cook that and you can work
on that
shenla
okay
if the if the fire didn't depend on the
wood then yes fires could break out
everywhere and they would go forever
and the fires would go would go for
always because they didn't have to have
fuel okay
uh dr barwon you know they would also
burn forever because they didn't have
fuel and the fuel can't run out okay
and you wouldn't have to go collect
firewood or buy gasoline
for your engine to run okay okay and
that's similar to the assertion that
the eye
wouldn't have to depend the eyeball
wouldn't they have to depend on its
causes
because it had no connection to them
and
it it wouldn't be the cause of seeing
because the scene
and the eyeball
and the chemicals in the eye were
separate and never overlapped okay you
got to think about it he's really making
the same argument that he made in the
last chapter
which is the point because this chapter
is used by the other guy to prove his
points in the last chapter
so don't forget when we're talking about
fire and firewood we're really talking
about the eye the astronomer and and the
stars okay
all right
the sun would really would burn forever
here's the sun okay
if the fuel the hydrogen that makes the
sun burn
and the sun were separate
then the sun would never burn out
because it has no fuel okay you would
just uh
you just have this fire going on forever
okay and this sun would never burn out
the abhidharma says our sun is going to
burn out
and
you know stephen hawking says the same
thing so probably he was
all right all right next verse
[Music]
and by the way uh this is a
this is a
what do you call it
this is a method employed by nagarjuna
again he will disprove something that
somebody else said
then he kind of gives the other guy
a chance to come back and then he
smashes him
okay so he punches him with the first
verse the guy comes back and then
nagarjuna knocks him out with the second
verse so it's called
means
nagarjuna's nailing it down okay so this
verse is kind of the same as the last
verse but it's meant to knock the guy
out forever
okay the first one just punched him all
right here we go
uh
della counted
and now suppose you think to yourself he
says to the other guy
section purchase
the burning is the one
don't forget we had fire agni
we had firewood
in dhanam
we had burning daha
okay and then this guy now the guy says
you know what
uh
the burning
is the wood
okay the burning is the wood
okay they're not separate and and
frankly
his example of a fire
is controversial it's difficult to
thresh it out in our own mind because
you know really when a piece of wood is
really burning it's kind of hard to
distinguish between where the fire ends
and where the wood starts
okay
congeets khan say that something you
know
if the burning is the firewood then what
burns the firewood except for the
firewood does the firewood burn the
firewood
that's naganji okay i'll say it again
that guy says you know what if you
really think about it the fire and the
firewood are kind of mixed up
and then the garden says yeah cool so
the firewood burns the firewood and you
don't need a fire
because the firewood isn't burning okay
he said the burning and the firewood are
kind of mixed up so the guy just said
yeah that's fine so just put a couple
sticks together and they can burn each
other
without fire
because the one stick is already mixed
up with the fire okay
like that
all right uh the burning of the wood
couldn't burn the wood what's the
picture but
oh that's why the boy is looking
confused
he just heard this verse
you know
if the burning was the fire
if the
if the burning was the fire then in one
match could burn another match without a
fire
okay got it that's why the boys looking
confused all right this boy represents
you guys
all right
next first what's it got to do with
mantra
oh
saying the mantra is carrying the cancer
okay
uh
so
then carrying the cancer is cured is
curing the cancer is caused by curing
the cancer and you don't have to do it
because the curing the cancer is the
mantra the mantra is carrying the cancer
the mantra cures the cancer the mantra
is
curing the cancer okay so carrying the
cancer is carrying the cancer and you
don't need a mantra you can just relax
okay
got it
the mantra
is
killing the cancer okay
then you don't need a mantra why
because curing the cancer can cure the
cancer why
because the mantra
is
curing the cancer
okay got it
all right by the way if you don't think
about it and you just give up
you won't be able to use mantras
so i'm sorry you have to think about
this stuff you have to go into retreat
at diamond mountain
in your spare time think about this
thing
okay and then you'll figure it out one
day you'll figure it out and then the
mantra will work okay which is exciting
all right
and i and by the way i mean it's gonna
take time
okay should i stop my mantras until i
can understand the garden i didn't say
that
keep doing the mantras they're going to
help you understand the continent and
then understanding the guardian will
help the mantras work okay all right
uh verse five i
[Music]
okay does the fire
is the fire the firewood
we already said no okay so the fire and
the firewood is separate right yeah
they're separate
okay and they can't overlap right right
they cannot overlap why there cannot be
an inch of the fire which is the
firewood either all the fires the
firewood or the fire is not the faraway
okay they got to be separate are they
separate yes
do they ever overlap no okay
okay so
they can't then the fire can't burn the
wood why it never touches the wood
no they do touch okay then they overlap
okay then the firewood is the fire right
then the firewood can burn the firewood
and you don't need a match
it's true okay it doesn't make sense
there's something weird going on you
just never thought about it
don't blame the guy tonight
some
the things you used to think were
causing things aren't causing things but
you spend your whole life lazy
not thinking about it and you keep
taking aspirin even though it doesn't
work half the time okay
all right
and you keep doing mantras even though
they don't work half the time okay
shenzhen
if that fire never touches the firewood
and they never overlap
separate
there cannot be a burning okay if the
fire
if the agni never touches the indana
right
there cannot be a daha
okay if the agni
never touches the interna
then there can never be a daha okay if
the
fire never touches the firewood
then there cannot be a burning okay okay
and if there's no burning there's no
nirvana what's that mean
if there's no
fire then there's no
fire going up
nirvana and this is where the word
nirvana comes if there's no fire
if the fire would never if the fire
never touches the fire wood
then there's not going to be any fire
and if there's no fire start then the
fire is never going to stop nirvana okay
then if it never stops me china okay
machina
which in the sanskrit is underrun under
one if there's no stopping of the fire
[Music]
then the fire is going to be hot forever
because
burning is part of the fire and it can
never go out and it can never start so
every time something is a fire it's
gonna burn forever it's just gonna burn
it will never lose its
swalinga in sanskrit linga means it's
fine
by the way which means uh
a male sign and a female sign but uh in
philosophy
it means
the fire would never lose it's hot and
burning
and it would burn forever
swallowing
it would keep its own sun
forever why
because it never went out why because it
never burned
why because the fire never touched the
farmer okay
something you gotta cook
all right we did the sanskrit part
already let's go
uh
yeah and by the way nagarjuna wraps it
up and says by the way if the fire could
burn the fire without any contact
then you could next picture
kim
then a match for lightest cigarette
without ever touching the cigarette okay
the fire doesn't have to touch the
cigarette if a fire could happen without
overlapping between the fire and the
firewood
then
somebody could
start a lighter
in
guadalajara and the cigarette will burn
in sedona
okay because they don't have to touch
okay according to you
all right we don't want to smoke anyway
i felt smeared about
all right next to
and 7.
now
this is one of those tricky spots in the
garjana
verse 6 is the other guy
and verse 7 is the guardian but he
doesn't tell you
okay now when you get really good at
reading
the scripture
you know which verse is fake and which
verse is right but if you don't you
better get a good commentary i've heard
many people explain
the other guy's position as the
guardian's position very eloquently
and it's just totally wrong
by the way in my opinion
i'm not aware of any good transmission
of the of the root text i don't think so
correct one i don't think so
the other guy says look when a man
touches a woman and a woman touches a
man they're different
what is that viva la difference
yeah a woman is not a man and a man is
not a woman and that's the only reason
they can touch if they were the same
thing then they would never touch and
then we wouldn't be here because our mom
and our dad would not have touched each
other right
so he says
look uh
women touch men and men touch women okay
and it's only if the firewood
and the
fire are separate
that you could have
touching between them things can't touch
if they're not different
a thing doesn't touch itself see i mean
a coffee cup can't touch a coffee cup
okay this coffee cup doesn't touch this
coffee cup
because it's not different from this
coffee cup this coffee cup is not
different from this coffee cup so they
could never make contact because they're
the same thing
to have contact things have to be
different
and then they can come to contact each
other therefore come on it's simple it's
like boys and girls
and then they touch they're different
okay so the fire and the firewood they
have to be different things the other
guy says i don't know why you're getting
so complicated
that's verse number six am i right yeah
now verse number seven is our answer
okay negotiate answer
made on shindogne
[Music]
okay
uh
now we go back to that verb we had where
one thing illuminates another thing or
one thing in delineates
another thing and he says you know what
celte me
cheeked on cheat me select
is it that
juice bottles define coffee cups and
coffee cups define juice bottles is it
that women define men and men define
women in that case they have to be
separate right
uh
if if if
if they touch quote like by the way
the other guy was talking about touching
in the sense of physically touching each
other
but nagarjuna takes it to
okay so
you can't really tell a man is a man
until he's in a room with a woman
okay you can't
distinguish
male
without female
okay in that sense they have to touch
meaning they have to be in the same
picture we got a picture here
i think
so
men and
male and female have to be in the same
photo
just to appreciate the difference
between a man and a woman okay they have
to be in the same photo
and then you can say oh look he's got a
beard she doesn't have a beard she's got
lipstick he doesn't have that i don't
know exactly but
okay so when they're in the same photo
when the juice bottle is next to the
coffee cup
then you can tell the contrast
defines each one
h1 defines the other
when you put them in the same frame of
your
camera your video right now
okay when you put them in the same frame
then this one
speaks to the difference between that
one and this one speaks the difference
from that one okay
uh
are you saying they define each other
yes okay
then you have to say they make contact
you have to be you have to believe they
make contact do they make contact
yes do they overlap no
do they make contact without overlapping
yes where's the point of contact it's
really overlap
okay
so don't tell me that males define
females and field males to find males
because they can't touch
no they have to touch to define each
other that's correct so they have to
overlap no one gets a lot they touch
without overlapping okay so there's no
point where they touch right there's no
point where one
overlaps the same area with the other
which is what contact means okay get
used to that
it's not that there's a tiny tip of the
of the mail that well
there's not a it's not that there's a
tiny tip of the bottle that that touches
the tiny tip of the coffee cup at some
point they have to overlap
or else they don't touch and then they
are disconnected
and you can't say one is defined by the
other
you can't say one is delineated aj
by the other you can't say that it's
very subtle and if you think about it
you'll get it okay don't give up don't
be lazy okay
you want to cure someone's cancer with
your medicine buddy mantras you've got
to figure this out
and i i i say
if you don't understand this you cannot
cure another person with your mantras
because then you don't know what you're
doing
then you're yelling at the husband who's
not in the kitchen
doing mantras without understanding them
to cure cancer
is like yelling at the husband in the
kitchen who's not there
okay it's the same thing
okay whoa
all right okay
uh
yeah we got that one hey we finished the
class
okay so uh think about it okay
can they touch without overlapping
no
well if they overlapped and they don't
touch
then they're the same thing then the man
is the woman at a little part of him is
the woman you know
and they don't define each other
okay
and
the point is for us
a mantra cannot cure cancer
if the mantra doesn't touch the cancer
and the mantra cannot touch the cancer
okay
so why the heck should i do mantras
because there's one thing causing the
mantra
which also causes the curing
well what's that
well that's saving life of animals
okay saving the life of the animals
makes the mantra work to cure cancer
think about that
all right see you guys in the next class
yay